<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-11-16T20:27:31+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">IDL Network</title><subtitle>The IDL Network, which is open to all, aims to support collaboration amongst educators of children and young people from 3 to 18 and beyond, including tertiary education. It will be particularly relevant for teachers, teacher educators, trainee teachers and probationers, school leaders, educators in further and higher education, and policymakers.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">IDL in Teacher Education, Part One: The IDL Implementation Gap</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/general/2022/11/14/idl-in-teacher-education-part-one-the-idl-implementation-gap.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="IDL in Teacher Education, Part One: The IDL Implementation Gap" /><published>2022-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/general/2022/11/14/idl-in-teacher-education-part-one-the-idl-implementation-gap</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/general/2022/11/14/idl-in-teacher-education-part-one-the-idl-implementation-gap.html"><![CDATA[<p>Within Scotland’s Curriculum for Excellence (CfE), interdisciplinary learning (IDL) is one of four contexts for learning (along with curriculum areas and subjects; ethos and life of the school; and opportunities for personal achievement). However, despite its supposed centrality within CfE, IDL has ‘not yet become a habitual learning approach in all of Scotland’s schools’ (Education Scotland 2020, p2). The first of two articles exploring the IDL implementation gap from the perspective of initial teacher education, this post exemplifies how, as a teacher educator, I support my primary teaching students in critical reflection on IDL guidance.  In the second article, I describe an approach to dramatic enquiry that is providing a framework for students to develop and implement their own IDL lessons.</p>

<p>There should be adequate time and space in initial teacher education devoted ‘to discourse relating to the nature of - and ways to - facilitate IDL thinking and learning’ (RSE 2020, p.9). For our student teachers, this includes critical analysis of national guidance on IDL.</p>

<p>Education Scotland’s 2020 publication <em>Interdisciplinary Learning: Ambitious learning for an increasingly complex world</em> aimed to ‘generate a set of recommendations from the profession, for the profession’.   Our teaching students unpicked some statements presented in <em>Ambitious Learning</em> about the difference between disciplinary and interdisciplinary learning.</p>

<p><em>Where, in a traditional classroom, the practitioner holds the keys to the next step, in an IDL experience every learner can express what they’re learning today, and why.</em> (Education Scotland, 2020, p.12).</p>

<p>The students observed that this can, and should, also be the case in inquiry-driven disciplinary learning.</p>

<p><em>Learning is joyful when learners are engaged in an IDL experience.</em> (ibid., p.14)</p>

<p>The students asked if disciplinary learning could not also be ‘joyful’. Is <em>all</em> IDL learning joyful? For <em>all</em> learners, at <em>all</em> times?</p>

<p>Two principal reasons for the variable consistency and quality of IDL in Scottish schools are a lack of conceptual clarity and a lack of exemplification (RSE, 2020). Despite a recent refocusing of thinking in Scottish education around IDL, criticisms of CfE guidance on IDL as being ‘well-intentioned but rather ill-defined’ (Humes, 2016:92) remain an ongoing concern, with pleas to address the lack of good exemplification still unheeded (RSE, 2020).</p>

<p><em>Ambitious Learning</em> certainly set my students’ brains whirring. Once again however, what is most notably missing from this national refocus on IDL are robust examples of practice. The recommendations set out in <em>Ambitious learning for an increasingly complex world</em> tend to focus on the secondary sector and on qualifications and timetabling. While this is understandable given the greater logistical challenges in secondary (STEMEC, 2016), the primary sector is still a long way from getting IDL uniformly right (STEMEC 2016; Graham, et al., 2017; RSE, 2020).  A balanced, systemic approach across both sectors is needed.</p>

<p>As teachers at the outset of their careers, my students are faced with a conundrum. If a lack of conceptual clarity prevails amongst many of their more experienced colleagues, exacerbated by a sparsity of robust IDL exemplification, how might they, as beginner teachers, be expected to develop their IDL understanding and practice?</p>

<p>Student teachers benefit from the demonstration of practical examples, along with opportunities for the students themselves to develop and implement IDL lessons (Harvie, 2018). In <a href="https://idlnetwork.org/2022/11/idl-in-teacher-education-part-two-planning-for-idl-through-dramatic-enquiry/">my second article</a> I describe how, in learning about an approach to dramatic enquiry, our students are developing their practical understanding of IDL.</p>

<h2 id="references">References</h2>

<p>Education Scotland (2020) <em>Interdisciplinary Learning: ambitious learning for an increasingly complex world.</em> Available at: <a href="https://education.gov.scot/media/mkomulen/interdisciplinary-learning-thought-paper.pdf">https://education.gov.scot/media/mkomulen/interdisciplinary-learning-thought-paper.pdf</a> (Accessed: 04/10/22). </p>

<p>Graham, C., Williams, G., Bryce, S. and McKenna, J. (2017) <em>Pillars and Lintels: The What’s, Why’s and How’s of Interdisciplinary Learning in STEM Education</em>. Edinburgh: The Royal Society of Edinburgh. Available at: <a href="https://rse.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/IDL_pillars_and_lintels_paper-1.pdf">https://rse.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/IDL_pillars_and_lintels_paper-1.pdf</a> (Accessed: 04/10/22)</p>

<p>Harvie, J. (2018) <em>Interdisciplinary Learning: A Chimera of Scottish Education?.</em> PhD Thesis. University of Stirling. Available at: <a href="https://dspace.stir.ac.uk/handle/1893/29326">https://dspace.stir.ac.uk/handle/1893/29326</a> (Accessed: 30/01/22).</p>

<p>Humes, W. (2013) ‘Curriculum for Excellence and Interdisciplinary Learning_’<em>, _Scottish Educational Review</em>, 45 (1), pp. 82-93. Available at:  <a href="http://www.scotedreview.org.uk/media/microsites/scottish-educational-review/documents/358.pdf">https://www.researchgate.net/publication/312456290_Curriculum_for_excellence_and_interdisciplinary_learningf</a>  (Accessed: 04/10/22). </p>

<p>Royal Society of Edinburgh (RSE) (2020) <em>Advice Paper: embedding interdisciplinary learning in Scottish schools</em>. Available at: <a href="https://rse.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2021/04/RSE_IDL_February2020.pdf">https://rse.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2021/04/RSE_IDL_February2020.pdf</a> (Accessed: 04/10/22). Science, Technology, Engineering and Mathematics Education Committee (STEMEC) (2016) <em>STEMEC Report 2016</em>. Available at: <a href="https://www.gov.scot/publications/stemec-report-2016/">https://www.gov.scot/publications/stemec-report-2016/</a> (Accessed: 04/10/22).</p>

<p>Featured image: <em>Teasel</em>. © 2022 Nick Hood.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general" /><category term="education" /><category term="enquiry" /><category term="idl" /><category term="skills" /><category term="teacher" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Within Scotland’s Curriculum for Excellence (CfE), interdisciplinary learning (IDL) is one of four contexts for learning (along with curriculum areas and subjects; ethos and life of the school; and opportunities for personal achievement). However, despite its supposed centrality within CfE, IDL has ‘not yet become a habitual learning approach in all of Scotland’s schools’ (Education Scotland 2020, p2). The first of two articles exploring the IDL implementation gap from the perspective of initial teacher education, this post exemplifies how, as a teacher educator, I support my primary teaching students in critical reflection on IDL guidance.  In the second article, I describe an approach to dramatic enquiry that is providing a framework for students to develop and implement their own IDL lessons.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">IDL in Teacher Education, Part Two: Planning for IDL Through Dramatic Enquiry</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/general/2022/11/14/idl-in-teacher-education-part-two-planning-for-idl-through-dramatic-enquiry.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="IDL in Teacher Education, Part Two: Planning for IDL Through Dramatic Enquiry" /><published>2022-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/general/2022/11/14/idl-in-teacher-education-part-two-planning-for-idl-through-dramatic-enquiry</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/general/2022/11/14/idl-in-teacher-education-part-two-planning-for-idl-through-dramatic-enquiry.html"><![CDATA[<p>In <a href="https://idlnetwork.org/2022/11/idl-in-teacher-education-part-one-the-idl-implementation-gap/">part one</a> of this two-part article, I exemplified how my student primary teachers critically examine CfE guidance on IDL. In this second post, I describe how I have been exploring IDL examples and implementation with students through <em>Mantle of the Expert</em> (MoE) - an approach to dramatic enquiry first developed by Dorothy Heathcote in the 1980s. MoE is currently experiencing a renaissance in pockets across the UK (e.g. <a href="https://www.woodrowfirstschool.co.uk/">Woodrow First School</a> and the <a href="https://www.mantleoftheexpert.com/news-post/new-project-on-the-welsh-borders/">Welsh Border project</a>).  </p>

<p>Through MoE, pupils operate within a fictional context as an expert team, working for a client who sets the team a commission leading to a range of curriculum-related tasks. For example, pupils might work as an expert team of archaeologists commissioned by the Museum of Cairo to plan and undertake the excavation of a newly discovered tomb.</p>

<p>A catalyst for an interdisciplinary approach is a problem or issue beyond the scope of a single subject that must be of relevance and real-life purpose to the learner (Barnes, 2015; Boix-Mansilla, 2005). MoE is an approach to curriculum integration which, as situated learning, can provide student teachers with an example of how to contextualise the kind of real-life purposeful problem that drives IDL.</p>

<p>In the first mantle I explore with students, pupils are an expert team of animal conservationists working in an animal sanctuary. The team are commissioned by an animal rescue organisation to reconfigure their existing enclosures to incorporate the needs of some newly rescued animals (Taylor, 2016). Pupils must acquire knowledge and skills across subjects such as science, maths and technologies, and synthesise these new understandings in order to address the problem.</p>

<p>While learning across the curriculum through MoE may not always be truly interdisciplinary (and it doesn’t have to be), well-planned commissions can lead to rich and purposeful IDL. For example, consider the IDL opportunities if the animal sanctuary team are commissioned with any of following:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Develop an education programme for the sanctuary</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Create a television documentary about the sanctuary and the animals it protects</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Plan a fundraising campaign to help support the additional animals</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Create an awareness raising campaign about endangered animals</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Plan for the reintroduction of a rescued animal back into the wild</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>One might ask where drama fits in all this. With an MEd in Learning and Teaching in the Performing Arts, I have a particular interest in the power and potential of drama to enhance learning across the curriculum. Sometimes referred to as process drama, this type of educational drama is not performance-focused, but instead involves pupils and teacher working and learning together through a range of drama conventions (or strategies). We can’t always bring the real, or ‘as is’, world into the classroom; however, through drama we can co-create an ‘as if’ world to give context to learning, providing learning with purpose and relevance (Edmiston, 2003). Through MoE, pupils work both inside and outside the fiction. For example, during the animal sanctuary mantle pupils might work inside the fiction in role as sanctuary workers to interview a local zoo owner. They might create still images of the public opening of the updated sanctuary or explore reasons for the animals needing sanctuary in the first place, presenting their ideas back to their peers as short role plays. At other times the pupils might work outside the fiction to research animal habitats or develop their understanding of scale and technical drawing. These newly acquired knowledge and skills would ultimately be applied within the fiction when, as an expert team, the pupils planned the new animal enclosures.</p>

<p>Last session, my PGDE students explored two different mantles before working collaboratively to plan mantles of their own, sharing some of this work in microteaching sessions.  Purposeful problems the students planned included:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>A team of astronauts tasked with applying their understanding of gravitational forces to design and pitch a new rollercoaster to the amusement park owners and park engineers.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>A team of expert scientists commissioned by an island government to investigate what is causing increasingly frequent tsunamis on the island. The commission includes the development of tsunami defense guidance.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>A Katie Morag themed mantle where a team of boat builders is commissioned by the people of the island of Struay to design a boat to meet the inhabitants’ diverse needs.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>The students were encouraged to analyse their work using Harvie’s (2020) model for IDL (see below), identifying where curriculum tasks might necessitate disciplinary learning, where aspects of their plans were multidisciplinary and which elements were truly interdisciplinary. The students reflected that there is, and should be, space for multiple approaches to learning within the curriculum.</p>

<p><img src="/images/Doig-Harvie.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>(Harvie, 2020, p. 58)</p>

<p>As part of research I was engaged in at the time, I undertook formal analysis of the impact of learning about MoE on PGDE student teacher understanding of IDL. Findings evidenced that MoE became a way for students to make sense of and connect their developing understandings of learning within and beyond subject boundaries. Students unanimously agreed that MoE was an effective way to exemplify IDL, and that it provided a supportive framework for IDL planning. I am working collaboratively with a colleague to integrate MoE throughout our undergraduate interdisciplinary module, providing further practical exemplification of its potential for effective curriculum integration.</p>

<p>Education Scotland’s (2020) <em>Ambitious Learning</em> paper describes classrooms where IDL is commonplace as exhibiting a ‘culture of thinking’, stating that in this culture ‘young people don’t just learn about history; they learn to think like historians. They don’t just do science; they learn to think like scientists’ (ibid. p.11)’. What better way to nurture this than by supporting young people in adopting the mantle of the expert?</p>

<h2 id="acknowledgements">Acknowledgements</h2>

<p>The animal sanctuary mantle was an adaptation of the work of Tim Taylor, a primary teacher and now teacher-trainer for Mantle of the Expert. You can find out more about Tim’s work and how other teachers are connecting the curriculum through MoE at the <a href="https://www.mantleoftheexpert.com">Mantle of the Expert</a> website.</p>

<h2 id="references">References</h2>

<p>Barnes, J. (2015) <em>Cross-curricular learning 3-14</em>. London: Sage.</p>

<p>Boix-Mansilla, V. (2005) ‘Assessing Student Work at Disciplinary Crossroads’, <em>Change: The Magazine of Higher Learning</em>, 37, pp. 14-21. http://dx.doi.org/10.3200/CHNG.37.1.14-21</p>

<p>Edmiston, B. (2003) ‘What’s My Position? Role, Frame, and Positioning When Using Process Drama’, <em>Research in Drama Education</em>, 8 (2), pp. 221-229. Available at: <a href="https://www.mantleoftheexpert.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/01/Whats-my-position.pdf">https://www.mantleoftheexpert.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/01/Whats-my-position.pdf</a> (Accessed: 04/10/22).</p>

<p>Education Scotland (2020) <em>Interdisciplinary Learning: ambitious learning for an increasingly complex world.</em> Available at: <a href="https://education.gov.scot/media/mkomulen/interdisciplinary-learning-thought-paper.pdf">https://education.gov.scot/media/mkomulen/interdisciplinary-learning-thought-paper.pdf</a> (Accessed: 04/10/22). </p>

<p>Harvie, J. (2018) <em>Interdisciplinary Learning: A Chimera of Scottish Education?.</em> PhD Thesis. University of Stirling. Available at: <a href="https://dspace.stir.ac.uk/handle/1893/29326">https://dspace.stir.ac.uk/handle/1893/29326</a> (Accessed: 30/01/22).</p>

<p>Harvie, J. (2020) ‘Interdisciplinary learning: addressing the implementation gap’, <em>Scottish Educational Review</em>, 52(2), pp. 48-70.</p>

<p>Taylor, T. (2016) <em>Mantle of the Expert: A transformative approach to Pedagogy</em>. Norwich: Singular Publishing.</p>

<p>Featured image: <em>Alliums</em>. © 2022 Nick Hood.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general" /><category term="education" /><category term="enquiry" /><category term="idl" /><category term="skills" /><category term="teacher" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In part one of this two-part article, I exemplified how my student primary teachers critically examine CfE guidance on IDL. In this second post, I describe how I have been exploring IDL examples and implementation with students through Mantle of the Expert (MoE) - an approach to dramatic enquiry first developed by Dorothy Heathcote in the 1980s. MoE is currently experiencing a renaissance in pockets across the UK (e.g. Woodrow First School and the Welsh Border project).  ]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How can maths teachers engage with the climate emergency?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/general/2022/10/03/how-can-maths-teachers-engage-with-the-climate-emergency.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How can maths teachers engage with the climate emergency?" /><published>2022-10-03T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-10-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/general/2022/10/03/how-can-maths-teachers-engage-with-the-climate-emergency</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/general/2022/10/03/how-can-maths-teachers-engage-with-the-climate-emergency.html"><![CDATA[<p>The maths classroom is often seen as a place of simple right and wrong answers and rote learning but it can and should be a place where children learn to think critically about complex real-life problems. What are we educating them for if it isn’t? The climate crisis provides an urgent, timely and ideal <strong>interdisciplinary</strong> context in which to set these problems.  Yet, sustainability and the climate emergency have turned out to be almost totally absent from staff professional development events, in-service day training, department meetings and general curricular delivery. Staff working groups are often not established or meet less often than monthly. Even in science course plans, climate change was only given the most cursory of mentions. Yet we are talking about an existential threat to humanity that should be top of every agenda.</p>

<p>During the first lockdown I met some like-minded (and equally concerned) individuals and we started to create events to give young people a chance to engage meaningfully with the issue. The first of these was a series of Scottish Parliament election hustings focussed on climate change which was eye-opening for candidates, who saw how well-informed and articulate young people could be.</p>

<p>Next, we decided to create a climate summit to take place around COP26, bringing together secondary school pupils from around Scotland and the Global South. This had several elements – sharing perspectives and stories; learning more about different countries and analysing data; and addressing real-life climate-related problems posed by the participants themselves. These activities gave young people a rare chance to take a leading role in their learning with scaffolding and facilitation from a teacher. This is how true Learning for Sustainability (LfS) must work if it is to be empowering and impactful for pupils.</p>

<p>1.5 MAX: Global Schools’ Summit finished with pupils making pledges for action in their schools and communities; this included rewriting school improvement plans to include LfS, tree planting, creating interdisciplinary units for the whole school to engage with, and creating locally-based climate board games. Plans received support from headteachers, MSPs and MPs in the Western Isles, and even HRH King Charles himself congratulated Boroughmuir High School (my school in Edinburgh) and Janakalyan Secondary School (Nepal) for their sterling work for the summit in late October 2021.</p>

<p>The pupils’ resolve and commitment to making a difference was nothing short of inspiring – and all that this involved was providing them with a dedicated window of time to plan, design and bring their ideas to life. A full showcase of the event is available at the PowerPoint link here: <a href="https://1.5max.org/survey2021/">1.5 MAX : 2021 : Survey Responses</a></p>

<p><em>“Through participating I realised just how compassionate and willing to make a change my young people are. They were all so motivated and had so many great ideas. I feel as a school we have not been offering enough opportunities for the pupils to be active in the fight against climate change so our pupil sustainability group will be starting up after the October holidays.”</em></p>

<p><em>– Rowan Cannell, Biology Teacher at Turriff Academy</em></p>

<p>We invite schools to join us for our next summit in 2023 (we are closed to new entrants for November 2022’s summit), but I recognise that not everyone has the time or inclination to take on a project as time-consuming as this.</p>

<p>Some useful starting points and resources for maths teachers wanting to bring climate and nature themes into their classrooms in a simple way may be found in the <strong><em><a href="https://idlnetwork.org/idl-resources/teaching-maths-in-the-context-of-climate-change-and-sustainability-resources/">Resources</a></em></strong> pages.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general" /><category term="climate" /><category term="cop-26" /><category term="education" /><category term="ideas" /><category term="idl" /><category term="mathematics" /><category term="resources" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The maths classroom is often seen as a place of simple right and wrong answers and rote learning but it can and should be a place where children learn to think critically about complex real-life problems. What are we educating them for if it isn’t? The climate crisis provides an urgent, timely and ideal interdisciplinary context in which to set these problems.  Yet, sustainability and the climate emergency have turned out to be almost totally absent from staff professional development events, in-service day training, department meetings and general curricular delivery. Staff working groups are often not established or meet less often than monthly. Even in science course plans, climate change was only given the most cursory of mentions. Yet we are talking about an existential threat to humanity that should be top of every agenda.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Christmas Break?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/general/2021/12/06/the-christmas-break.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Christmas Break?" /><published>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/general/2021/12/06/the-christmas-break</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/general/2021/12/06/the-christmas-break.html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s that time of year when many teachers, pupils and parents feel like they are crawling to the festive finish line, eager for a mince-pie-filled break from all things school related.</p>

<p>Yet Christmas is a time jam packed with hidden learning opportunities, spanning every curricular area you can shake a figgy pudding at. Moreover, the best part of this holly jolly reality is that these activities won’t even feel like learning!</p>

<h3 id="christmas-cards">Christmas Cards:</h3>

<p>A quick search on Google or Instagram will present a merry plethora of glittering ideas. Motor skills, artistic work and obviously writing all come together to create a festive greeting card but why not extend the learning with a pop-up element or some tessellation of snowflakes or holly? And we shouldn’t overlook the potential digital literacy skills that come with finding an address and google mapping the nearest postbox.</p>

<h3 id="wrapping">Wrapping:</h3>

<p>Having just prepared an IDL lesson for my class all about wrapping paper, I was amazed at how much learning you could pack into this life skill. As a general rule, if you measure and then double the length of the perimeter of your gift, you’ll have enough paper to neatly wrap your present. There’s discussion and calculations to be had about area and perimeter; around sustainability and responsible consumption. However, why buy paper when you can create your own? Carving into polystyrene blocks (you might have an early present or two delivered in a chunk of it) you can create Christmas stamps that can create effective patterned paper when dunked in red, green and white paint.</p>

<h3 id="shopping">Shopping:</h3>

<p>If you’re travelling to someone else’s house for Christmas, why not have your little elves phone the host and ask if they need anything picked up: crackers, table decorations, a snow shovel. They will have to take some notes over the phone, before creating a list and researching the best place to buy. You could provide them with a budget and providing they can figure out the change left over, allow them to buy some carrots for Rudolph/a sickeningly sugar-filled tub of candy cans with what’s left over.</p>

<h3 id="board-games">Board Games:</h3>

<p>Playing board games (and card games) are highly complex activities. No surprise they can lead to arguments and wondering why on earth you invited your Uncle Sandy around in the first place. Patience, turn taking, negotiation, planning and strategising, rolling and counting - a list longer than a 500 pack of clear white fairy lights. But if you want to add that personal touch, have your little helpers create their own board game. Choosing a theme, creating an objective, designing the board, fine tuning the rules, creating the chance/forfeit cards and crafting the playing the pieces: it’s an activity that takes time and resilience but results in a red-nosed reward that will have the kids glowing from antler to ear.</p>

<h3 id="christmas-adventures">Christmas Adventures:</h3>

<p>Christmas craft is a primary school tradition that sees children across the country returning home with questionable toilet roll creations vaguely resembling Rudolph after the Christmas party. But time off school presents the opportunity to create truly beautiful pieces of Christmas art. Why not go for a walk and take photos of winter scenes on your journey? Woody, bare branches; white, icy grasses; glistening, frozen water. Print them out to compile a Christmas collage and create a border of natural materials foraged on your travels.</p>

<p>I haven’t even touched on baking and decorating cakes, creating sustainable gifts, performing songs and plays on Christmas Day, designing and running a family quiz or even being in charge of filming and documenting the annual Boxing Day game of charades. Needless to say, the Christmas break might be sold to us as a holiday but the truth is it’s two weeks of endless learning opportunities: enough to stuff a turkey with.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>Blair Minchin is a Scottish Primary Teacher who has achieved a global following by sharing ideas and experiences from his classroom on social media. His daily video lessons have helped children to continue learning at home during the pandemic.</em> <em>Find him on Twitter at</em> <a href="https://twitter.com/mr_minchin">@mr_minchin</a>.</p>

<p>Featured image: <em>Robin</em>. © 2018 Nick Hood.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general" /><category term="christmas" /><category term="ideas" /><category term="idl" /><category term="primary" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It’s that time of year when many teachers, pupils and parents feel like they are crawling to the festive finish line, eager for a mince-pie-filled break from all things school related.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Climate Change, Environment and Sustainability: Teaching Resources</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/general/2021/11/12/climate-change-environment-and-sustainability-teaching-resources.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Climate Change, Environment and Sustainability: Teaching Resources" /><published>2021-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/general/2021/11/12/climate-change-environment-and-sustainability-teaching-resources</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/general/2021/11/12/climate-change-environment-and-sustainability-teaching-resources.html"><![CDATA[<p>The 26th UN Climate Change Conference in Glasgow is a critically important intergovernmental meeting of world leaders and scientists if irreversible climate change is to be avoided. It is also part of a much greater and broader long-term challenge of mitigating wider environmental degradation world-wide that threatens the sustainability not just of humanity but of all life on Earth. These challenges and related opportunities are all deeply interdisciplinary in nature.</p>

<p>Learning and teaching resources on these and related topics spanning most curriculum areas and many facets of climate, environment and sustainability have been collated from various sources in our recently updated <a href="https://idlnetwork.org/idl-resources/">resources page</a>.</p>

<hr />

<p>Featured Image © UK Met Office, University of Reading <a href="https://showyourstripes.info/">#showyourstripes</a> CC-BY-4.0</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general" /><category term="climate-change" /><category term="cop-26" /><category term="education" /><category term="resources" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The 26th UN Climate Change Conference in Glasgow is a critically important intergovernmental meeting of world leaders and scientists if irreversible climate change is to be avoided. It is also part of a much greater and broader long-term challenge of mitigating wider environmental degradation world-wide that threatens the sustainability not just of humanity but of all life on Earth. These challenges and related opportunities are all deeply interdisciplinary in nature.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Should future learning be problem-based?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/general/2021/08/25/should-future-learning-be-problem-based.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Should future learning be problem-based?" /><published>2021-08-25T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-08-25T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/general/2021/08/25/should-future-learning-be-problem-based</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/general/2021/08/25/should-future-learning-be-problem-based.html"><![CDATA[<p>It is now widely recognised that, from both theoretical and practical perspectives, the old ways of structuring knowledge in a curriculum by dividing learning into academic subjects or disciplines can look antiquated. </p>

<p>From the theoretical perspective, the internet - with its hyperlinks and networked knowledge - has made us all aware of the historically conditioned or even arbitrary nature of dividing subjects into discrete units like English, Sociology and Biology. Knowledge, in the phrase popularised by Peter Morville, is <a href="https://intertwingled.org/">intertwingled</a> and its categorisations contingent. From the practical perspective, when 86% of graduate employers <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/education/2020/may/18/employers-are-slashing-graduate-jobs-but-students-mustnt-lose-hope">‘do not care’ what degree students studies at universities</a>, why do we insist that they continue to study almost exclusively in such disciplinary categories. Is there a better way? </p>

<p>Enter Problem-based learning – or PBL. Many readers of this blog will be familiar with PBL. Its history goes back at least to <a href="https://helpfulprofessor.com/pragmatism-in-education/#:~:text=In%20education%2C%20pragmatism%20is%20an%20approach%20to%20learning,and%20focus%20on%20topics%20relevant%20to%20students%E2%80%99%20lives.">Dewey</a> and his ideas of practical education, and PBL has been a stalwart of <a href="https://www.bmj.com/content/326/7384/328">medical education</a> for some time*. The basic idea – that humans are, fundamentally, ‘<a href="https://books.google.co.uk/books/about/All_Life_is_Problem_Solving.html?id=W0jP04qn0uoC&amp;redir_esc=y#:~:text=All%20Life%20is%20Problem%20Solving%20is%20a%20stimulating,Cold%20War%20and%20after%20the%20collapse%20of%20communism.">students of problems, not disciplines’</a> and that this should be reflected in our education systems – has support also from Karl Popper, the great 20th century philosopher and, of course, it has been tried in many schools and colleges <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/teacher-network/teacher-blog/2013/dec/08/project-based-learning-high-tech-high-teacher">all over the world</a>. </p>

<p>If PBL has such solid support from so many perspectives, why hasn’t it caught on more? </p>

<p>I think one of the main issues is that we don’t really know what progression looks like in PBL - outside of disciplines. My colleague Dilly Fung, Pro-Director for Education at the London School of Economics, describes this as the challenge of creating a ‘<a href="https://www.ucl.ac.uk/teaching-learning/sites/teaching-learning/files/extract_from-a-connected-curriculum-for-higher-education-chapter-4.pdf">throughline</a>’ in a curriculum. We know what it looks like to get better at solving maths problems or problems in medicine. But problems related to sustainability? Or poverty? Or migration? There seems to be a class of problems – often called ‘wicked’ problems – which, although arguably of most importance to humanity, are hard to pin down in the sense of knowing how we are getting better at tackling these problems. At the <a href="https://www.londoninterdisciplinaryschool.org/">London Interdisciplinary School</a>, the new university being founded in London, we want to approach this educational problem head-on. We believe the current education system is not serving many students well and wish to equip them better to deal with the sorts of big, complex and important issues they will encounter after graduation. </p>

<p>At the centre of our curriculum, but changing each term, is a ‘problem statement’, running through a central 18-credit module. This problem statement could be related to sustainability, AI and ethics, public health or another real-world complex problem. These statements are scoped by faculty, according to our collective expertise, and students have some choice in the final statements they choose to tackle. This central, problem-based module is strongly supported by ‘methods’ modules from across a wide range of arts and sciences: scientific experimental method, writing methods, statistical methods, data science methods, ethnography, arts methodologies etc. All students encounter this range of methods in year 1 and then are allowed to refine and take further their learning of specific methods in years 2 and 3, though never abandon entirely either all science/maths or all qualitative methods. </p>

<p>We will also teach explicitly some ‘inter’, ‘post’ or ‘supra’ disciplinary thinking such as Systems Thinking, <a href="https://fs.blog/mental-models/">Mental Models</a> or <a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/03080188.2019.1670441?journalCode=yisr20">Superconcepts</a>. But note that we do not wish to teach a rigid post-disciplinary methodology – that would defeat the object of allowing students to shape their own curriculum and advance their interdisciplinary understanding - processes we think best suited for the sort of creative problem-solvers and radical lifelong learners we would like to graduate. </p>

<p>We are thus committed strongly to interdisciplinarity and to each student shaping their own approach to problem-solving through collating and connecting their own suite of methods. We ask students to articulate and evidence their approach as fruitful through the various assessments we set in relation to the problems. These may be written reports, videos, campaign strategies etc. Our assessments will look for enriched interdisciplinary understanding of the problem and thoughtful, sometimes even original, ways to tackle it. This approach requires a rethink of the <a href="https://www.carlgombrich.org/post/towards-curriculum-as-network">curriculum as a network of connected concepts and methods</a>, individualised and capable of being narrated and owned by the student. Each such knowledge network is individual but coherent (a property of networks in general) and better aligned both with the interests of the student and with the exploding number of <a href="https://www.burning-glass.com/research-project/hybrid-jobs/">‘hybrid jobs</a>’ required in today’s knowledge and digital economies. </p>

<p>We do not underestimate the challenge of reframing how we think of knowledge structures and their relevance to the lives of our students. Old categories and old metaphors die hard! But nothing really worth doing is easy. We need new ways of thinking, visualising and speaking in order to support our students in the sort of problem-based education which is closer to their interests. And an interdisciplinary, networked curriculum is an important step. </p>

<p>*Note there are sometimes distinctions made between <em><strong>problem</strong></em>- and <em><strong>project</strong></em>-based learning. However, both are distinct from more traditional subject-based learning and start with students considering a problem to tackle or a project to complete which cuts across two or more traditional subjects.</p>

<p>……………………………………………….</p>

<p><em>Carl Gombrich is a co-founder of the new London Interdisciplinary School (</em><a href="https://londoninterdisciplinaryschool.org/"><em>https://londoninterdisciplinaryschool.org</em></a><em>), where he is Academic Lead and Head of Teaching and Learning. He was previously Programme Director for the Liberal Arts and Sciences (BASc) programme at University College London (UCL).</em></p>

<p>Featured image: <em>Culross</em>. © 2021 Nick Hood.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general" /><category term="connections" /><category term="education" /><category term="learning" /><category term="networked-knowledge" /><category term="pbl" /><category term="problem-based" /><category term="project-based" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It is now widely recognised that, from both theoretical and practical perspectives, the old ways of structuring knowledge in a curriculum by dividing learning into academic subjects or disciplines can look antiquated. ]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Has the time to connect finally come?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/general/2021/06/03/has-the-time-to-connect-finally-come.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Has the time to connect finally come?" /><published>2021-06-03T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-06-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/general/2021/06/03/has-the-time-to-connect-finally-come</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/general/2021/06/03/has-the-time-to-connect-finally-come.html"><![CDATA[<p>Three recent events, which at first seemed totally unconnected, prompted me to think about where we are with interdisciplinary learning (IDL) in our schools. </p>

<p>The first was my re-reading of notes I took at a pre-Covid RSE lecture given by Prof. Ian Goldin of Oxford University.  In it he said “Today is the best day of our lives because tomorrow will be much more complex.  There is no historical precedent for where we are now.”  Prof. Goldin’s words at the time struck me as being prophetic and have proved to be just that with the clear exposure of the complex connections we have at a global level shown by the devastating impact of the Covid pandemic over the past year.</p>

<p>The second event was an article in the Herald newspaper which said that researchers suggested the work of Leonardo da Vinci could help schoolchildren tackle the climate crisis.  The researchers argue that replicating da Vinci’s ability to work across areas of knowledge rather than being stuck in subject “silos” can help learners make connections and nurture the problem-solving skills necessary to overcome the existential challenges of the future.</p>

<p>The third event was an inspiring lecture given by Prof. Jonathan Powles from the University of the West of Scotland in which he suggested that the central mission of education is about making connections.</p>

<p>As all teachers will be well aware, the Curriculum for Excellence support document, <em>Building the Curriculum 3</em>, pointed out that learning at both primary and secondary stages “should be made available in a range of ways including interdisciplinary learning and a range of opportunities which ensure a broad approach, enabling, for example, a coherent understanding of environmental issues” and that “Well-designed interdisciplinary studies at these stages often provide highly motivating contexts for learning which can help children to see links between and the relevance of different aspects of the experiences and outcomes.”.</p>

<p>The refreshed narrative on Scotland’s curriculum, prepared in response to a recommendation made by the Organisation for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD), reinforces the important role of IDL.  It states that the curriculum should include the space and opportunities that enable children and young people to make connections between different areas of learning to help deepen understanding and make the curriculum more coherent and meaningful to learners.</p>

<p>The refreshed narrative also exemplifies in more detail the four fundamental capacities at the heart of education and central to Scotland’s curriculum.  One of these capacities is to:</p>

<p>“recognise the knowledge, skills and attributes that children and young people need to acquire to thrive in our interconnected, digital and rapidly changing world”.</p>

<p>In Scotland, we have even gone as far as to have integrative projects in the four Scottish Baccalaureates at SCQF Level 7 as one way of encouraging interdisciplinary working and learning.</p>

<p>Despite these curricular directives, and although there has been progress, meaningful IDL in Scotland remains a largely unfulfilled aspiration in the curriculum of many schools. I have seen for myself over many years as an HMI, very good primary and secondary teachers doing all they can in their lessons to make connections across areas of the curriculum to enhance and give coherence to learning.  Some of the most effective has been where teachers, either individually or collaboratively, have been bold and had the confidence to allow learning to develop “organically”, with children and young people leading the exploration of a topic or theme as their enquiry and creativity directs them.  However, all too often, teachers have pointed to the fact that, while valuable, such opportunities are restricted by overly bureaucratic and restrictive demands of planning placed on them.  Headteachers and curriculum planners point to the need to “cover an already over-loaded curriculum” and “preparation for subject examinations” which limit the scope for meaningful IDL. </p>

<p>To get an updated perspective on IDL, I turned to some of my Finnish colleagues where the new Finnish school curriculum, introduced in 2016, includes the requirement that all learners in each year of their nine-year basic education (ages 7-15) undertake one ‘multidisciplinary learning module’ or ‘phenomenon-based learning module’ as they have become known.  This caused much curiosity at the time with questions being asked as to why such an apparently successful education system (albeit based largely on PISA scores) was rejecting its traditional, subject-based curricular structure in favour of something so radically different.  Of course, as it has turned out, Finland’s subject-based curriculum remains in place although the annual ‘multidisciplinary learning module’ is now embedded into the curricular structure of all schools across the country.</p>

<p>The arguments made in Finland for these ‘multidisciplinary learning modules’ and a multidisciplinary approach to learning being integral parts of the curriculum are no different to those made for IDL as part of Scotland’s Curriculum for Excellence.</p>

<ul>
  <li>They can promote and encourage the more active engagement of children and young people in their learning which can enhance their understanding of complex, interconnected local and global issues.</li>
  <li>They provide a context in which learners can apply knowledge and skills from different subjects and make connections across learning, allowing them to develop important skills like communication, critical and creative thinking, problem solving and teamwork.</li>
  <li>They can provide a means by which learners have more freedom to build their own knowledge, which is transferable, and gives them a deeper understanding of what they are studying.</li>
</ul>

<p>Finnish researchers suggest it is still too early to determine the impact of their multidisciplinary module.  While there are examples of good practice emerging, so too are suggestions that national guidance on implementing the modules is too broad, resulting in variation of how the modules are being implemented across the country.  Some concerns have been expressed about how the modules relate to the Finnish curriculum’s seven transversal competencies and how the modules support progression in knowledge and skills in subjects.  Finnish teachers also report the need for more support and training in delivering the multidisciplinary module.</p>

<p>There are undoubtedly lessons to be learned from Finland’s determined efforts to give much greater prominence to IDL in the curriculum.  The Finnish government clearly sees the merits in its children and young people engaging in interdisciplinary modules and learning as a means of enhancing and connecting their learning in our increasingly complex and interconnected world.</p>

<p>As we in Scotland are being urged to use the disruptive effects of the pandemic as a call to radically reimagine our education system, including what and how we teach, will IDL feature?  Has its time to help learners make much-needed connections in their learning finally come?</p>

<p><em>Ken Muir was Chief Executive and Registrar of the General Teaching Council for Scotland for seven years until early 2021 and was previously HM Chief Inspector of Education. He is now an Honorary Professor at the University of the West of Scotland.</em></p>

<p>Featured image: <em>Forth Shore at Kinghorn</em>. © 2021 Nick Hood.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general" /><category term="connections" /><category term="education" /><category term="finland" /><category term="idl" /><category term="pisa" /><category term="post-pandemic" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Three recent events, which at first seemed totally unconnected, prompted me to think about where we are with interdisciplinary learning (IDL) in our schools. ]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Is it hard to be soft?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/general/2021/05/21/is-it-hard-to-be-soft.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is it hard to be soft?" /><published>2021-05-21T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-05-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/general/2021/05/21/is-it-hard-to-be-soft</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/general/2021/05/21/is-it-hard-to-be-soft.html"><![CDATA[<p>Assembled in the room were the senior civil servant and his top team responsible for education in Scotland. My job was to present what 22,000 employers big and small, public and private told us about the people they recruited in the past year.</p>

<p>The data told an unexpected story.</p>

<p>New recruits were poor at talking and listening, working with one another and with the public, and poor at elementary planning or problem solving. Employers of lower paid people, for example jobs in care and retail, had the greatest dissatisfaction. Graduates recruited, we were told, had the same soft skill shortage, just to a lesser extent.</p>

<p>After two hours of close questioning and discussion, the headman closed the session by saying, “ Thank you that was most interesting. But it has nothing to do with us”.</p>

<p>A large elephant stood in the corner of the room and was quietly ignored. Then and now the Scottish mind set and education policy is the need for more people with higher skills – that is degrees. And why? Because that was what employers wanted.</p>

<p>Except that was not what employers were telling us. At that time I was the Senior Director for Skills and Learning in Scottish Enterprise. One of my colleagues who led Future Skills Scotland (soon to become chief economist at the Royal Bank of Scotland) turned to me as we were shown out and asked, “Did he really say that?”</p>

<p>Roll forward to just before the first pandemic lockdown. Olli-Pekka Heinonen the former Minister for Broadcasting and now the Director General for Education in Finland was on a visit to Edinburgh.</p>

<p>Heinonen explained how six countries: Finland, Hong Kong, South Korea, Singapore, Canada and Estonia had been collaborating. Each country was at or near the top of the Programme for International Student Assessment (PISA). They wanted to prepare their children for the next twenty years in a world of growing complexity, risks, unknowns and the unknowable.</p>

<ul>
  <li>They created a typology to understand the route forward:</li>
  <li>The industrial society was about body and hands.</li>
  <li>The information society was about brains</li>
  <li>The interaction society, which they see forming, is about heart and humanity, with soft skills becoming more and more important.</li>
</ul>

<p>Cup your hand to your ear and listen to what Scottish employers tell us. It helps if you use your good ear.</p>

<p>How are the soft skills, the heart and humanity, promoted in our children and the education system?</p>

<p>Heinonen directed us to four ways Finland had achieved its current education success. Trust came first, teachers had a lot of autonomy, there were few tests getting in the way of education. Second, teachers were highly qualified, as a profession it was difficult to get into and was highly rewarded.</p>

<p>Third, parents and families were well supported from pregnancy right through to school age. Fourth, across Finland there was a coherent story, a consensus on supporting children and education.</p>

<p>Maybe all this is interesting, but has nothing to do with us. Or perhaps when we stumble on a truth the best thing to do is to dust ourselves off and continue uninterrupted down the same path.</p>

<p>Another path is possible in Scotland. It requires putting the 3 Ps before the 3 Rs. It is the 3 Ps that do the most to enable soft-skills, self-control, agency and the flourishing of heart and humanity.</p>

<p>The three Ps are: Preconception; Pregnancy and Parents. It is about what we, people plus public services, do to engage and support parents. Timing is important. The most sensitive period of the formation of life is the first 1000 days.</p>

<p>Take a trawl through different types of biological, neurological, psychological research and long-term data sets and the arrow points towards this conclusion.</p>

<p>Employers in Scotland may have alerted us to an important truth. Hard skills do matter, but in general we are short of soft skills – interacting with other people, problem-solving, communication, adaptability, empathy, resilience. Soft skills help with employment and the likelihood of well-being.</p>

<p>Sequence matters, self-control, agency, sticking to task are the bedrock on which higher order skills get built and interdisciplinary learning thrives.</p>

<p>The same soft skills help us to navigate life.</p>

<p>Ask the Finns; they have just been judged the country with the greatest well-being for the umpteenth time in a row.</p>

<h5 id="references">References:</h5>

<p>Jay Belsky, Avshalom Caspi, Terrie E. Moffitt, Richie Poulton (2020) The Origins of you: How childhood shapes later life, Harvard University Press.</p>

<p>Alan Sinclair (2018) Right from the Start: Investing in parents and babies, CCWB press.</p>

<p><em>Alan Sinclair was for 5 years Senior Director for Skills and Learning in Scottish Enterprise, with responsibilities for Modern Apprenticeships and youth employment. In 2000 he was awarded a CBE for training unemployed people. He has a passion for supporting parents and children.</em></p>

<p>Featured image: <em>Queensferry Crossing</em>. © 2021 Nick Hood.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general" /><category term="3-ps" /><category term="employers" /><category term="finland" /><category term="parenting" /><category term="pisa" /><category term="skills" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Assembled in the room were the senior civil servant and his top team responsible for education in Scotland. My job was to present what 22,000 employers big and small, public and private told us about the people they recruited in the past year.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Is IDL just another Educational initiative?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/general/2020/12/17/is-idl-just-another-educational-initiative.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is IDL just another Educational initiative?" /><published>2020-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/general/2020/12/17/is-idl-just-another-educational-initiative</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/general/2020/12/17/is-idl-just-another-educational-initiative.html"><![CDATA[<p>The education system is notorious for its ‘new initiatives’. Understandably, we repeatedly aim to raise attainment by motivating the less than enthusiastic learner, but instead produce short-term solutions that rarely fulfil this expectation. Each decade or so we find that success in engaging the disengaged continues to elude us. Many documents are written, many person hours engaged and much funding provided to resolve this issue but frequently it is patchy, any success is short lived, and verifiable analysis of the given initiative unclear and lacking in concrete and measurable results.</p>

<p>This is to be expected when mass education has narrow common goals. The common perception that the purpose and aim of education was lots of “good” qualifications and a place at a “good” college or university was perhaps acceptable when life for many was predictable and “good” jobs were secured with such qualifications and social mobility was enhanced. This has not been the case for many years. The document “21st Century Skills” (Trilling and Fadel 2012) highlighted this in 2009. Since then we have become aware that traditional accepted learning and career pathways have been disrupted. We must change too if we are to make education relevant, necessary and engaging. We know what we are aiming for in helping to create a successful 21st century citizen, but so far the route we have travelled is strewn with ambitious but unsuccessful initiatives.</p>

<p>Unlike successful businesses, education is not good at moving and changing quickly. CfE notwithstanding, our schools still use a 19th century structure of teaching in short subject specific periods, and assessment remains a 20th century subject-driven exam system which mostly tests and values memory recall. In my opinion, most ‘raising attainment’ initiatives may give us short-term gains in a league-table obsessed society but are too often doomed to fail.</p>

<p><img src="images/Picture-1.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Sea level rise (melting ice, Greenland’s Southwestern coastline)</strong><br />
Image credit: NASA / JPL-Caltech</p>

<p>If you are reading this, then you are probably in broad agreement with what I’ve written. The bigger question is - how do we work towards making the changes we all want to see? Is IDL just another initiative that will have its moment in the sun and fade away when the document writers move on, targets change or the funding is withdrawn? Fair questions, as many of us who started teaching in the 1990s have seen government and local authority initiatives come and go. I feel no contrition in admitting that I saw my own enthusiasm become jaded as I broached my third or fourth initiative. Like so many others I moved away from the classroom. I felt I could contribute so much more by focusing on one specific aspect of education and there, at least give my best to something I could believe in. So what has given me new hope and brought me back to support IDL in the classroom?</p>

<p>Firstly, IDL is not a government or local authority driven initiative, although it is a CfE context for learning and support is encouraged for this approach. Secondly, its development and delivery have no specific funding, and thirdly it is being driven by enlightened and enthusiastic teachers and educators across Scottish education, not by pre-determined numerical targets in attainment.</p>

<p>Yes, we will still have to work within the prescribed learning outcomes and benchmarks, and by the constraints of subject-dominated SQA exams, but the driver is not ticking boxes to meet targets. The people driving IDL understand that the current education system may often meet required targets but frequently misses the point. By the integrated use of the principles of pillars (discreet learning and teaching within subjects) and lintels (applying the learning in two or more core subjects to solve problems or provide deeper understanding) learning has a real purpose - a purpose which students, their parents and especially teachers can all engage with, implement and fully evaluate.</p>

<p>As we all know, purpose and the ensuing motivation are the real drivers of meaningful learning. If collectively, we can embrace Interdisciplinary learning and allow it to infiltrate and drive current practices, we may eventually succeed in meeting Curriculum for Excellence’s original worthy mission, which is often lost in a plethora of guidelines: successful learners, confident Individuals, responsible citizens and effective contributors. If, in the oft-quoted phrase, we can, “measure what is valuable rather than value what is measurable”, then I can look forward to the next generation being better equipped for the 21st century in a curriculum which is driven by motivation to find answers and solve problems rather than just answering questions.</p>

<hr />

<p>Trilling B and Fadel C (2012) 21st Century Skills: Learning for Life in our Times. Jossey-Bass</p>

<p><em>Featured Image “Factory producing smokes” by Alexander Tsang (Unsplash.com) CC-BY-NC-4.0</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general" /><category term="education" /><category term="idl" /><category term="initiatives" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The education system is notorious for its ‘new initiatives’. Understandably, we repeatedly aim to raise attainment by motivating the less than enthusiastic learner, but instead produce short-term solutions that rarely fulfil this expectation. Each decade or so we find that success in engaging the disengaged continues to elude us. Many documents are written, many person hours engaged and much funding provided to resolve this issue but frequently it is patchy, any success is short lived, and verifiable analysis of the given initiative unclear and lacking in concrete and measurable results.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What is IDL?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/general/2020/11/05/what-is-idl.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is IDL?" /><published>2020-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/general/2020/11/05/what-is-idl</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/general/2020/11/05/what-is-idl.html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>“The student who can begin in early life to think of things as connected…..has begun the life of learning”</strong>. Mark van Doren (poet, writer, critic) 1943.</p>

<p><em>Interdisciplinary learning (IDL) is a way of thinking and learning in which learners draw on knowledge, understanding and skills from two or more subjects in order to solve a problem or advance our understanding of a concept or idea that extends beyond the scope of any one subject.</em> IDL enables the transfer and application of subject knowledge and language to other areas of learning and to new problems. It is not a substitute for subject-based learning – on the contrary, disciplinary and interdisciplinary learning are complementary and interlinked. IDL cannot exist separately from disciplines but is founded on strong disciplinary knowledge, understanding and skills. It should complement and enrich subject learning, facilitate learning across subject boundaries, and enable students to use their learning beyond the situation in which the learning occurred.</p>

<p>Featured image: <em>Whitelee Wind Farm</em>, <em>nr Glasgow</em>. CC BY-3.0 Author: BJ Mullan</p>

<p>The development of IDL requires breadth of subject knowledge and skills. That is why it is commonly developed collaboratively. The principles and practice of IDL as a way of thinking and learning apply across all areas of learning and teaching, including further and higher education.</p>

<p>IDL is often used (and misused) as a general term for various types of learning that involve the wider use, connection and application of disciplinary knowledge (‘making connections between subjects’), such as (for example) multidisciplinary-, project-based, inquiry-based - or problem-based learning. <em>All have thei</em><strong><em>r place</em>.</strong> </p>

<p>Interdisciplinary learning and multidisciplinary learning are often confused. Simply linking discrete subjects with no immediate connection together around a theme is <em>multidisciplinary</em>, not interdisciplinary.</p>

<p>“Conflicting understandings of what IDL is” was recognised by teachers and educators at the RSE IDL conference as one of the major challenges of IDL implementation. This is why a concise working definition of IDL is important in providing a ‘benchmark’ for its development and practice, even although in practice there are many possible creative contexts, starting points and approaches to the development of IDL and some ‘fuzziness’ and latitude around this definition.</p>

<p><img src="images/Slide1.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Pillars, lintels and foundations</p>

<p>A helpful metaphor for IDL is that of <strong>pillars, lintels and foundations</strong>. IDL should continue to be founded on deep and coherent pillars of subject knowledge, understanding and skills. Interdisciplinary learning will lack rigour and utility if not part of a structure in which the <em>disciplines are the pillars</em>, with the <em>interdisciplinary working as the lintels</em>. Without the disciplinary pillars, the interdisciplinary lintels will fall. The pillars and lintels are supported by <em>foundations</em> – competences, aptitudes, basic knowledge, skills and methods in and across all subjects, including literacy and numeracy.</p>

<p>There is an ever-increasing need for the integration of both specialist and broad knowledge in the modern workplace and in the wider world. Subject-specific knowledge is no longer the primary determinant of suitability in most graduate recruitment. However, IDL is not just about equipping students with more useful skills for the workplace; it is more broadly about providing students with experiences that foster a lifelong love for learning, creativity and community.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.rse.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/RSE-IDL-Conference_Introduction-Paper-2019.pdf">Click here</a> to access the <strong>RSE IDL Conference Introduction paper</strong> (2019).</p>

<p><a href="https://idlnetwork.org/2020/11/what-is-a-discipline-the-importance-of-subject-knowledge-in-idl/">Click here</a> to read more about <strong>disciplines</strong>.</p>

<p>Featured image: <em>Pillars, lintels and foundations</em>. © Colin Graham 2020</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general" /><category term="interdisciplinary-learning" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[“The student who can begin in early life to think of things as connected…..has begun the life of learning”. Mark van Doren (poet, writer, critic) 1943.]]></summary></entry></feed>